Guide to the Baruch Nadel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Other files, 1918-1985; Series III
  Folder 76 contains Menahem Nadel's biographical memoir of his involvement in he-Ḥalutz and the Labor Zionist youth movement in Russia and other documents relating to this movement. Materials in folder 77 also document Zionist youth work, particularly that inspired by Ber Borochov. The file contains items about ha-Noar and ha-Hugim ha-Marksistim b'Erets Yi'sra'el, issues of be-Mefneh, volumes issed by Sefriyah Marksistit of which Menaḥem Nadel was an editor, and writings by him. Printed copies of articles by Chaim Arlosoroff are in folder 79 along with scattered documents concerning plans to rescue Rumanian Jews in 1944 and issues of a socialist youth group newsletter ha-Degel ha-Adom. The writings of Sholom Shlogar are included in pamphlets and issues of he-Ḥevrah in folder 80. Folder 81 contains additional printed material, clippings, and photographs relating to Lehi and Abraham Stern. Series III also includes a rare Israeli stamp issued prior to May, 1948. A xerox copy of the stamp is included in folder 82.
  Box 9 contains four volumes of the journal Sulam from 1949 to 1952. The journal, a monthly general periodical, reflects the thoughts of the Ḥerut Party in Israel.
  The material in this series remains in the order established by Baruch Nadel. Each folder in box 8 contains explanatory notes by Nadel concerning the contents of that folder.
  - Nadel, Menaḥem and he-Ḥalutz, 1918, 1985, undated (Box 8, Folder 76, Reel 8U)
  - Nadel, Menaḥem, 1923-1985, undated (Box 8, Folder 77, Reel 8U)
  - Marxist youth movements, Undated (Box 8, Folder 77, Reel 8U)
  - Labor Zionist movement, Undated (Box 8, Folder 77, Reel 8U)
  - Greenberg, Uri Zvi, 1920, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 78, Reel 8U)
  - Arlosoroff, Chaim, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 79, Reel 8U)
  - Jewish Agency for Palestine; Hebrew Committee of National Liberation, 1944, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 79, Reel 8U)
  - ha-Degel ha-Adom, Undated (Box 8, Folder 79, Reel 8U)
  - Shlogar, Sholom, 1941, undated (Box 8, Folder 80, Reel 8U)
  - Nadel, Menaḥem, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 80, Reel 8U)
  - The Old Jewish Cemetery of Prague, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 80, Reel 8U)
  - Lehi, 1944-1978 (Box 8, Folder 81, Reel 8U)
  - Stern group, Undated (Box 8, Folder 81, Reel 8U)
  - Miscellaneous Hebrew publications from Jerusalem, Kiev, and New York, 1923-1971 (Box 8, Folder 82, Reel 8U)
  - Sulam, 1949-1952 (Box 9, Folder 83-84)
    General
    This material has not been microfilmed.
- Additional material, 1847-1991; Accession 1992-M-035
  This addition is composed of brochures, posters, reports, and other types of printed material, as well as photographs, which document Jewish life in many locations. The materials are arranged by country of origin. One folder at the end of the addition contains additional photographs of Abraham Stern.
  - Notes on material by Nadel, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Belgium, 1932 (Folder 2, Folder 68)
  - France, Circa 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Germany, Circa 1900-1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Israel, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Palestine, Circa 1919-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Oversize (Folder 2, Folder 68)
  - Poland, 1868, 1905-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Russia, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Switzerland, 1847 (Folder 2, Folder 68)
  - Ukraine, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - United States, 1940, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stern, Abraham: photographs, Circa 1913-1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Additional material, 1955-1992; Accession 1992-M-072
  - Interview concerning the death of Yoseph Trumpeldor in 1920, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between Sholom Ya'acobi and Nathan Yallin Mor concerning the "Case of Shmu'el", 1974 (Box 1)
  - Nadel's notes concerning this accession, 1992 (Box 1)